A Finding Aid to the James Edward Davis papers, circa 1917-1970, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
James Edward Davis papers
circa 1917-1970
Archives of American Art
Davis, Jim, 1901-1974
AAA.davijame
Archival Resource Key
3.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter, photographer, and filmmaker James Edward Davis measure 3.8 linear feet and date from circa 1917-1970. They highlight Davis's career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed and photographic material, and artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection and material lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels N172, N68-86A, N738, and 430-433 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Biographical / Historical
James Edward Davis (1901-1974) was a painter, photographer, and filmmaker who worked primarily in New Jersey. Born in Clarksburg, West Virginia, Davis specialized in the abstract and surrealist styles and his artwork was heavily inspired by the zeitgeist of the 1920s. He graduated from Princeton University in 1923 and studied painting and sculpture in France with Andre Lhote for three years. Davis taught at multiple places during his career including Lawrenceville School (1933-1936), Princeton (1936-1942), and the Moholy-Nagy Institute of Design (1947). Davis is also known for his experimental abstract films that use mobile designs of transparent plastics and controlled illumination. His paintings have been shown at the Museum of Modern Art, the Addison gallery, and the Princeton and Yale University Art Museums. He died in Princeton, New Jersey at the Princeton Medical Center at the age of 73 on September 20, 1974.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sketches, designs, working papers related to Davis's art films, the John Marin letters, and drawings were lent for microfilming by James E. Davis in 1967 and 1968. Papers were donated in 1969 by James E. Davis and Rosalind Kossoff.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art also hold an oral history interview with James Edward Davis conducted 1971, August 10 by Paul Cummings.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reels N172, N68-86A, and N738) including sketches, designs, working papers related to Davis's art films, the John Marin letters, and drawings. Loaned materials were returned to the lender.
Arrangement
This collection consists of seven series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1954-1966 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1940-1969 (.6 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1920-1960 (.8 Linear feet: Boxes 1 and 2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1956-1967 (.1 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1945-1969 (.2 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1919-1970 1(.9 Linear feet: Boxes 2-5)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1946 (.1 Linear feet: Box 5)
Scope and Contents
The James Edward Davis papers measure 3.8 linear feet and date from circa 1917-1970. Biographical materials consist of a resume, an interview with Davis, and certificates related to his career and schooling. Correspondence consists of letters between himself and his agent Rosalind Kossoff, Frank Lloyd Wright, John Marin Jr., and others. Writings includes notebooks pertaining to his many projects and personal business records are composed of documents relating to his career and his time spent in Princeton, New Jersey, as well as artwork appraisals. Printed material is made up of exhibition announcements and catalogs, news clippings, press releases, and other documents. Photographic materials include photographs from various film projects and exhibits, as well as personal photographs. Artwork consists of a group of sketches showing a figure in motion.
Photographers -- New Jersey -- Princeton; Painters -- New Jersey -- Princeton; Filmmakers -- New Jersey -- Princeton; Drawings; Marin, John, 1870-1953; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959
- Biographical Material, circa 1954-1966; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes Davis's resume, certificates relating to his career, and the transcript of an interview with Davis by Bruce Friar.
  - Resume, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview with Davis by Bruce Friar, Transcript, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Film Assembly, Recognition of Merit Certificate, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kiskiminetas Springs School, Certificates, circa 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, circa 1940-1969; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .6 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is between Davis and Rosalind Kossoff, Frank Lloyd Wright, John Marin Jr., and Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, as well as others.
  - Corresponcence (1940s), circa 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence (1960s), circa 1960-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kossoff, Rosalind (1940s), circa 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kossoff, Rosalind (1950s), circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-19)
  - Kossoff, Rosalind (1960s), circa 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-29)
  - Marin, John Jr., circa 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo, circa 1945-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Vanderpool, Wynant D., circa 1947-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Wright, Frank Lloyd, circa 1950-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Films by Davis, circa 1948-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Writings, circa 1920-1960; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .8 Linear feet Boxes 1 and 2
  Writings includes notebooks consisting of notes and narratives on each project, news clippings and other articles, drawings, and photographs. Also included are an article written by Cecile Starr and miscellaneous writings.
  - By Davis, Archival Resource Key
    - "Continuity Sheet for Film Pertaining to Chicago", by Davis, circa; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Through the Looking Glass", circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Notebooks, Archival Resource Key
      - "Exhibits-Collections-Etc. of Paintings", circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - "Experiments in the Visual Expression of Motion", circa 1920-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
      - "Notes on Frank Lloyd Wright", circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
      - "Notes, Photographs, Etc. on John Marin", circa 1940-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - "Pertaining to the Films of Jim Davis", circa 1949-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      - "Plastics and Illumination", circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
      - "Photography", circa 1952-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "The Visual Arts and Space", circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
      - "Visual Design, Notes, and Illustrations", circa 1936-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - By Others, Archival Resource Key
    - Article for June Issue of House Beautiful (1954), Draft by Cecile Starr, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1952-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1956-1967; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include materials relating to the Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts, a signed petition to keep Davis as a resident of Princeton, New Jersey, and the artist record for Davis at the Museum of Modern Art. Also included are bills and receipts for artwork sales, and artwork appraisals.
  - Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Museum of Modern Art Department of Photography, Artist Record, circa; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Residency Petition for Princeton, New Jersey, 1961, Jul. 25; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Artwork Appraisals, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bills and Receipts for Artwork Sales, circa 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Printed Material, circa 1945-1969; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs, a convocation program for the Kiski school, news clippings and press releases, and publications featuring Davis's artwork.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1950-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1950-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kiski School Convocation Program, 1956, Jan. 21; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - News Clippings, circa 1949-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Press Releases, circa 1954-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Publications Featuring Artwork, circa 1945-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1952-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Photographic Material, circa 1919-1970; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 2-5
  Photographic materials consist of photographs of images from Davis's films. Also included are photographs from his personal life.
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Titled, Archival Resource Key
    - "Calligraphic Designs", Photographs and Slides, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Figures in Motion", circa 1919-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - "Human Figure - Static", circa 1919-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - "Japanese Calligraphy", circa 1953-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Ice Forms", circa 1953-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Landscape", circa 1925-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    - "Light Reflections", Photographs, circa 1937-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    - "Light Reflections", Photographs and Slides, circa 1937-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Mirrored Effects", Photographs, circa 1952-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - "Mirrored Effects", Slides, circa 1952-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "The Path of Motion", circa 1937-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - "Portrait and Genre", circa 1925-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Prism Refractions", circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Plastics and Illuminations", Exhibit, circa 1932-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - "Still Life", circa 1927-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Time Exposures", circa 1937-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs from Films, circa 1920-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Duplicates, circa 1920-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1920-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Artwork, circa 1946; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 5
  Artwork consists of a group of sketches showing a figure in motion.
  - Sketches of Figures in Motion, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)